knowledge is power
[Music]
i was in uh last month i was in i'm from
uh washington state originally and last
month i was i was over there uh working
doing a little traveling work but um
yeah yeah i'm in austin now i've been
here for about a year and a half
um you know mostly been inside during
covet and everything which is actually
how i ended up here i was coming to
write a book
and i was gonna be here three or four
months and then covet happened a few
other things and i'm actually about to
get back on the road in september
october so
yeah so you're going to be traveling is
austin going to be your your main locale
though um you know uh christy thompson
is here uh she is kind of the
uh we like to refer to her as a leader
that we use a term called first follower
which is not really meant in the way
most people think of that there's this
wonderful video on our resources page
called the dancing guy
and it's all about how the person who
comes
to whoever had the idea and goes that's
a good idea
that's the real leader
yeah almost like giving them permission
hey that thing you're doing is okay
that's good yeah
and let's other people know it's also
safe too
yeah is it from have you seen that video
of there's a music festival of a guy
dancing by himself
okay yeah yeah okay that's the dancing
guy video and i don't know if you know
the origin of it's the most popular
piece
on our resources page which has like
30 40 references including buckminster
fuller and hans rossling who is one of
the greatest statistician storytellers
ever to live who basically says we need
to really relax
about overpopulation fears and all of
that sort of stuff and between all those
elements they love the dancing guy more
than anything else
that's funny that's how it goes right
you don't get to choose what
proliferates you just got to follow what
does you know put it out there you know
i think that's a good theme of of
anything we want to really talk about i
was on a podcast recently and when i
shared some of our point of view
you know he said i'm a quaker and i'm a
buddhist and everything you're saying is
stuff we've been saying for thousands of
years so you know how are you adding
anything
new to the conversation which is a
really good question and i said well
first of all you know we're framing it
in maybe more of a five or six year olds
version
you know and as einstein said loosely
translated if you can't explain it to a
six-year-old you don't quite have it you
know
and i think that uh
i think we need a thousand flowers
on the topic of how do we really
overcome
war it's not just enough to call it
conflict like the way people converse is
very warlike
and if you as a generality it's you know
there's exceptions of course right but
as a generality humanity
comes from seventy thousand years of war
we we use language
in order to make life happen
never mind change
uh and and if our conversation is an
inheritance
of 70 000 years of war we can't sort of
really expect that we just wake up in
one generation the 21st century and put
an end to that without a lot of
conscious attention
to solving that problem
right but but building that conscious
attention is it's likely a lot of what
your work is right
accidentally to be to be really frank
but yes
yeah
wow okay well let's um let's let's get
into it i was thinking uh if you don't
mind daniel i was just going to read
your one page just the the first couple
little paragraphs and then we could jump
off into it after there just a little
intro
cool um
so welcome daniel i appreciate you
appreciate you
taking time out of your day to do this
so daniel is the founder of is there
enough a provocative new conversation
about the intersection of survival
economics and social justice justice
he is also the co-founder of impact
launch pad a uk-based venture studio for
social impact incubation and development
working from a book a conversation and a
unique social research experiment that
has taken him to 22 countries mr
madeleine is it matt alone matalon
madeleine
mr
mr matalon is asserting the humanity's
biggest existential threat is not
climate change tribalism or inequality
but our inability to make agreement with
each other at the level we require to
address our challenges
yeah i totally agree um so so what what
what is your
what's your elevator pitch of your work
so if someone's like hey what what do
you do what is usually your your
sentence back
i'm working on the world game turning it
into a business model you ever heard of
that
and the person usually hasn't and i say
well it was invented by this guy
buckminster fuller who you'd know by the
geodesic dome but
also had 50 predictions for the year
2049 of those 50 came true certainly
in a list of the top 100 minds of all
time
and
he proposed that the world game
was how to make the world work for 100
of humanity
and he chose language really carefully
so he added some other words to it like
with conditions
like
uh
in the shortest time possible through
spontaneous collaboration without uh
ecological offense or disadvantage to
everyone or his conditions
we stumbled onto posing a question
question is really simple is there
enough just three little words
and when we throw that stone in the
water into conversation and has other
sort of applications that are more
specific than the generality of that
question it deliberates a conversation
and i'm reporting to you from thousands
of hours and 22 countries looking at
this
that takes people down a path of
reevaluating
what enough is
not
uh
abundance which i was hoping people
would wake up to abundance for 25 or 30
years lecturing among why there really
is abundance
uh and how that's actually the norm of
the universe and scarcity is something i
would propose that we
manufacture that's my point of view on
the question of is there enough
but the deliberation of what enough is
surprise to me turns out to be highly
personal as well as global at the same
time i have no idea how it does that
um
but it but it was sort of the idea
in the world game about mr fuller
talking about 100 of humanity is how can
one individual think about 100 of
humanity it seems impossible
and yet the posing of the question of is
there enough
has generated a responsibility in people
that the answer to that question
is their responsibility it's their
choice right and as some people
reinterpret it
i'm reporting to you now some people
reinterpret the question a lot of
different ways and one of them is well
how do i make the world work for me
comes out of this question is there
enough because it's not just 100 of
humanity but sometimes a hundred percent
of my world
this can be true in a relationship it
can be true in business it can be true
in a nation
so
i guess the only thing you could say
that we're adding to the picture
is the posing of this question as a
prelude to a new deliberation about
agreement
because if we want to make the world
work
what does that mean work for a hundred
percent 100 is like towards a more
perfect union right it's a it's a
calculus right it's an ideal but if we
talk about the work part
we define that
and other people would define the answer
differently so i want to be clear but we
define
that
making wealth more available for more
people in less time is a trajectory we
can absolutely measure
so my professional work is devoted to
that
and the question of is there enough just
sort of came out of
working on that strategy and talking to
people and it just bounced out of the
space and became a phenomenon that took
me to 22 countries so far
yeah so so in your travels when you go
to these different countries and when
you do pose the question
what do you find like what's what what's
the response across the table what what
is typically
kind of the first thing that comes into
people's minds what do we think about
when you ask that question
if you don't mind i'd rather tell you
the most surprising response that's
consistent in 22 countries which people
come back with
am i enough
[Music]
followed closely by are we enough
very big surprise to me in fact you know
i have a book coming out
and i would ideally not want it to be
thought of in a self-help section i mean
we categorize that's what consciousness
is largely right
i don't mind that people use it though
for personal
transformation
uh i'm i'm impressed by it because it's
an it's an it's a surprising thing
so i have sort of more fun with that
part about it because i know what my
intentionality that i think is so
important and then there's this
surprising thing come out of it but
we have found that people engaging in
this conversation can make their own
world work better not just the world
work better
it is a it does have a personal
development transformation
think about it i mean if if you're able
to make more agreement tomorrow than you
made today
everything you're working on becomes
better right
right yeah
so so it is sort of so it's an
inadvertent you didn't intentionally
write a self-help book but it is kind of
a an automatic turning towards the self
like um
so has this whole thing kind of been a a
personal uh sovereignty sort of thing
like uh the essence of this is you know
we have to learn how to love ourselves
or or feel that ourselves is enough in
order for it to
expand out into being enough for
everyone yeah i mean
people can watch this visually see me
bristle the list a little bit as you
came to it so you see my
apparent
discomfort
uh with the concept of of personal
development as that aspect
it's simply that
i think clarity comes out of the
question and when we have clarity we can
begin to make better choices it's as
simple as that
my partner in our business side of what
we're doing our for-profit social impact
side
says people think that we're idealists
but actually we're clarifiest
is that we that's how we think of it
inside the building so so i
i'm not sure if that answers your
question except to simply say that
people use this deliberation to reassess
their values it's kind of like maslow's
hierarchy without having to talk about
maslow which is why i can have a
conversation with a group of
kindergartners about this which i was
once challenged to do
and and all i did with them
strangely enough
all i did was have a conversation with
them about how they got their breakfast
that morning
and every story was about collaboration
interesting so so is that what you're
pointing to is this
this
this expanded view of collaboration um
what
how is the conversation with the
kindergarteners an example of the wider
view of what you guys are are teaching
and and showing to the world
the purpose of this initially was to
make the world work in an aggregate way
but of course a five-year-old's not
thinking about that they're looking
after their own needs right
and if five-year-olds can look after
their own needs
through this
human superpower that we think we have
that makes us more human than human
a step towards compassion before telling
everybody they have to be more
compassionate than they are
you understand that distinction
right
creating some cognitive empathy before
we demand and there is a little bit of
culture that demands
a certain level of emotional empathy
that i'm not sure we're ready to step
into fully in 100
but we can understand each other we can
tolerate each other and if a
five-year-old can understand that
it's not
how pretty you are how fast you run or
what car your daddy drives
it's how you can be valuable to
everybody around you
like that's a selfish thing if you could
turn that into a selfish thing you see
greed goes away
it becomes unnecessary but mr fuller
used to say that
if you really want to deal with a bad
system don't fight the existing reality
just create a new one
and conversation creates reality not
always of course that's why
people have oh there's all talk and no
action well without talk there's
definitely no action
that's new right so the question is what
kind of talk will have the tendency to
produce the most what we would call
action obviously right action
philosophically
um but it can be used for any action i
mean anybody listen to my voice knows
that an agreement was made
to create a slave triangle that funded
the world right that was an agreement
too there's some very bad agreements in
the power of agreement right agreement
is power
but can a five-year-old make an
agreement with another five-year-old
yeah
they just created some power they'd have
to take it from each other
right and i'll just say like power is
also mystified you talk about
demystifying things or we could have a
nice conversation about what power
really is
because because
i would love to dive into that yeah what
do you mean what
what i actually have i i have not done a
lot publicly for many years
uh but somebody just unearthed a 1996 or
1997 interview with me about this topic
and uh
power's just basically the simple
ability to get things done my my dog
does not have the power to lift a cup
but because of his relationship with me
if i need to move his ball for him
you know he now has the power
to move the ball right
um so
power can be created
doesn't have to be taken it can be taken
we can fight about it but at the end of
the day when we're finished fighting
we're gonna have a treaty usually set by
the winner which is where your inclusion
problem is in history right but it's the
agreement that create the post-war is
where the economic boom is let's say
this is throughout history not just
after world war ii
right
so the treaty is the engine that creates
the results the same thing happening in
the united states right
you're getting to the place where people
going wait actually we do need some
institutions you know what i mean let's
do some deconstruction but also like
bucky would say you don't take down the
system you create a new one right just a
waste of time this is the thing that i
think even people
who have created identity with
themselves around war inadvertently
right to be partisan you know before
values is sort of what that is right to
be about my common identity with each
other rather than what our common
identity is about is a very war like
prep
um you know precedent
what we are
uh
what we're talking about is the ability
to make power not take power you can use
fire
to burn down your house or heat your
house you can use a knife to you know
cut yourself free from bondage and you
can kill somebody it's the tool of how
and why it's used and for what purpose
that and if you think about it if you
ask the question is there enough hash
it's a hashtag is there enough we we put
it as three words together a hashtag is
there enough to to establish this
conversation and apply that lens to
power is there enough power
oh
you want to see some emotions fly in a
clubhouse room
just talking about it so it is this very
general
neuroplastic
uh
um
vagueness designed to get people to you
know sort of have this reassessment with
themselves about their values but you
now apply it as a lens
uh jacob to a topic like is there enough
water
which our company impact launchpad has
done
about 80 hours of research on new
technology to produce
mine
uh the atmosphere for water not have to
take it from the ground it's very viable
technology
um so when we have a conversation called
is enough water we'll bring some experts
together and talk about that when we
talk about is there enough justice we
bring experts together to talk about is
there enough justice
so it has this generality of stirring up
the pot for people to begin to recognize
that they have more power than they
realize they do they have more ability
to get things done than they give
themselves uh credit for when they're
talking about all the people in power
that are doing things to them they're
not spending any conscious time thinking
about what do i have the power to do
today and what can i have the power to
do tomorrow and the power to do tomorrow
is only based on how much agreement i
can create i could force somebody into
agreement yes
but it's very hard like it's very time
consuming it you know it just doesn't
make sense this is the real thing that i
think can be a breakthrough is not just
appealing to people on why they should
give up arms in a way of being you know
great for humanity because only certain
amount of people think that way but if
we can make it in their personal
selfish interest
to make as much agreement as they can in
their life can you imagine what ripple
effect that creates
so
i'll just land the plane so to speak on
this point to rally it to the personal
individual in the psychology of it
the first chapter of the book that we
have coming out in 23 and i say we had
something of a community project in that
sense but i'll have my name on it
um as an author is uh it had an orphan
chapter
i didn't know where it went and it
turned out it was the kickoff of the
book and it was basically about
uh
how we perceive our identity
i'm an amateur i'm not an academic i'm
not a professional so i'll say things in
very simplistic terms so it does a
disservice to psychology
for me to simplify identity in this way
but for this purpose it makes sense
as i'm saying that basically we are our
history
and we are our choices
joe dispenza would say we are our
choices period
he believes in that so much i just found
out recently i feel we carry our history
and we make our choices and if we don't
recognize and embrace that history that
got us here
i think that struggle is very very
difficult
i can embrace my history
and also make choices and over time
those choices become new history
and that's who we are so
that's really what the this conversation
sets in motion
our goal is for people to have this
conversation themselves which is what
we're teaching people to do
yeah i i really like that um
i was thinking a lot about what you said
about identity do you think that um
would we all have to kind of be on the
same page of what our history is i mean
i kind of get down these rabbit holes of
um
you know what what what are the pyramids
actually and uh
you know where psychedelics uh to the
birth of our consciousness and all these
sort of things like
they make me rethink what i was taught
in school
i'm like i don't i don't really know
like if we have a a unified version of
how our history really goes i mean of
course we do our best to put together
the the things that we have but a lot of
it is kind of blocked off by
you know um
just different people with different
interests and
it benefits certain groups to not have
certain truths or certain versions of
stories
you know out to the rest of the world do
you think that we would all have to be
kind of on the same page of our history
and kind of what we are as humans even
because i'm not sure that we all even i
mean a lot of people don't really think
about the fact that we come out of the
earth that we really are part of this
evolutionary
you know thing happening
so do you think that um
i i don't know
i just i guess i just think about the
fact that i'm not sure that we all agree
on or we already think about that much
our origins of what we are and i think
that is probably an important piece of
the puzzle right
it is the the name the name of the book
that we're putting out is called the
first agreement people ask us what's the
first agreement and i say to have one
let's start with one
yeah okay
um
the answer your question about do we all
have to be on the same page to have one
agreement
no we don't
um
is the history
vastly important that's why i included
in identity and i don't agree with joe
that we're only our choices right right
i respect him greatly i think he's a
genius by the way yeah
but but i think that if you look at all
conflict
as a whole let's say 90 of it is all a
debate about history
just one sec you're gonna edit right
i'm on a podcast
sure
no problem
okay
um
so
um all of our conflict
is about our our stories
and
we need to resolve those conflicts we
can't ignore them
it's vitally important
that we get to know
what the other perspective is if it
feels other to me
in order for us to mine through that for
agreement like disagreement is not not
part of agreement i don't know how you
make new agreement without mining
through disagreement actually and i'm
now speaking from some amateur social
research at this point
you know beyond my initial insights
whenever they were
we have some sub conversations
in is there if you go to is there
enough.org it's kind of an agreement
academy and there's like a link that
says academy and has some subsets and
one of those subsets is called core
conversations or i think it's called the
core or whatever
and one of them is that
again this can be artificial at first
but if we started in conversation with
our sameness and then our difference
we end up with a different result than
if we go to the automatic like well i'm
different than most people i've said
that phrase many times in my life i'm
sure you have too on whatever topic you
think
is especially unique right it's like we
want people to know that about us
that's us
like meaning me versus us meaning you
and i which us are we gonna start with
is what it boils down to the last
chapter of the book
is called people like us
and you can find yourself using that
phrase organically authentically
truthfully in life
in conversation
you i feel like you're probably moving
in a good direction towards what we're
talking about of this ideal value
i think the history issue is critical in
that cognitive understanding like
we are our stories
right all of our victimization
that we have suffered all of us have
basically all of our stories all of us
have suffering
and we don't feel understood because
nobody's ever suffered like i have in
the way that i have about this this
we're so alone in our suffering we think
we are i mean in a way like true like
you know who can understand your
suffering the way that you do like bug
mr fuller also said he said no one
again this is a guy who made up words
right so he chose every word super
carefully right he said no one has ever
seen anything
outside of themselves
wow
yeah
yeah so if i can pierce through some
approximation of trying to put myself in
your shoes if i can create some
incentive for myself to do that not
because i should or shouldn't or just
just as a game again it's a world game
that we're talking about not a war game
but a world game and you can't have a
war without a war game and bucky would
say you can't have
a world that works without a world that
works game so if you want a world that
works game it all begins with
conversation
that tends like you know the way we'd
say that the arc of history bends
towards justice if you want conversation
that tends towards collaboration and
agreement it will come from me knowing
your story as you see your story not
telling you why your story's not real
even if by the way your story
i would call false
based on some other facts like i learned
this from jonathan hype
the
the righteous mind for anybody who wants
to look him up and study values of
conservatives and liberals why why good
people
disagree about uh
uh religion and politics basically
but you know there's this
sense
uh and i don't know if our way is you
know the best way or the right way or
anything we need a thousand flowers
blooming but so far what we're
progressing on is stimulating a
conversation where people can get to
know what the other guy's enough is
that's basically what it boils down to
when it comes to to that
because what i see is not enough and
what you see is not enough
is absolutely like a fingerprint and you
can ask yourself the question what
enough is in them in a month from now
it'll be different
where have you seen and then where do
you see this um
maybe slipping off the tracks like i
think about have you heard of the um
the idw the intellectual dark web it's
sam harris eric weinstein brett
weinstein and those sort of guys um
i i was really into a lot of their
content the last couple years and i
really was fascinated by this thought of
getting
intellectual people who kind of think um
in a metacognitive way together and
discuss kind of what's going on in the
world and why are we thinking
differently and how do we make sense of
it better and where are conversations
going awry um
and
i i heard i can't remember exactly who
was involved but i had heard at some
point there was a big meeting of all
these you know smart people in a room
sort of thing and it ended up digressing
like even the mediator couldn't seem to
pull it in it seemed to be like a all
right whatever guys we're done and this
the project kind of just fell a little
have you heard of this or do you think i
haven't heard of that event i haven't
heard of that event i certainly know the
the crew
and the people around it i'm a you know
avid follower of lamar and so you know i
have sort of tangents in all of those
rooms uh from other people that i work
with for many years
um and i think what a testament to how
absolutely difficult it is to create
agreement and collaboration in the world
like
let me say this in the strongest terms i
know how to say
uh we are like alcoholics who haven't
admitted that we're alcoholics when it
comes to this topic right
we don't admit can i tell you the number
of times that i have spoken to
leaders you and i
absolutely admire and know are making
good in the world okay
who i've dropped this conversation on at
times and wanted to accept themselves
from the crew who don't know how to
collaborate because look at my life and
look how i know how to collaborate about
the identity of i'm a collaborator
rather than looking at what's good about
that question about how could we become
super
human
at agreement
nothing less than that mandate right
and
you know i'm on clubhouse and i'll
listen to a guy talk about 20 years of
his research over three or five minutes
on a topic right really powerful stuff
and the next person who speaks will go
that's really cool i agree with about
ninety percent of that but i noticed you
didn't include anything about that
right
this is common in conversation so i can
imagine
and and i'm i'm really not trying to
judge people do that i'm just pointing
out this is the thing right when you
talk about history everything i just
said is history
up to this moment right now every
conversation i just referred to in
clubhouse is history the question is
which is really why we ask is there
enough when people have the conversation
the second question comes up and the
second question is called
what are we going to do about it
right which you do not get to ask unless
you ask question number one of his
fairness wouldn't make any sense
because what are we going to do about it
the it in that sentence refers to what
there's not enough of
once you're getting to the it's really
the not enough campaign
but it wouldn't work that way if we
called it
enough and so by examining what there's
not enough of
with clarity now because we're not
worrying about the things that really
are enough of that's a big thing that
people get out of this conversation by
the way is a lot of relief
about things they worry about that they
realize they don't have to but once we
then put a laser focus on things we
better freaking worry about like like
you know our existential threats to
humanity
once we get to that place then it's what
are we gonna do about it and you have
this may sound
you know
quite adamant or fixed about that but in
my view you only have two roads to go
there which is conflict
or agreement
war agreement i mean as ben ferenz the
last living nuremberg prosecutor 102
years old to this day still living who
put the term crimes against humanity
into law for the first time hit the
summation of his life is law
over war that's how he looks at it from
a you know his
dean legal
expertise i look at it as an amateur
non-academic and i say
agreement
is the is the every man's law a
five-year-old can make an agreement but
they can't write a law you see what i'm
saying and if we had that culture of
that respect and recognition for what
giving our word means and living up to
that just for the sake of that even when
it's inconvenient because we trusted the
long-term economic economic value not
just moral value i'll leave the moral
side out for people who don't aspire to
that let me just give you the economic
reality is that wealth
not money
money's a part of wealth but real wealth
is produced by agreement not resources
that's completely false
the idea that
we would even debate this sometimes when
you talk about history we debate
questions we have
no benefit
debating like was climate change
man-made or not what a distraction that
was
yeah so much wasted time on that subject
right and i think the one about about
wealth is
you know
is wealth a fixed thing do we do do we
really live on a planet of i keep
hearing this stated like it's a fact
that we live on a planet of finite
resources
i'm sorry that's
that's never been proven in the history
of humanity
never there's not one time we ever ran
out of a resource we didn't replace with
another the problem is us not the
resources
[Music]
yeah wow okay so so where do you see
so so after you guys get get this book
out um are you gonna continue touring or
like like what is your what is your
process afterwards how do you keep keep
having these conversations and who are
the type of people that i mean of course
you know podcasters and just inquisitive
minds and whatnot but who are the type
of people you're you're searching for to
have these conversations with and maybe
kind of um you know
enlighten through conversation and kind
of open open us up to um even being
about being able to have these
conversations sure
um so there's a few questions in what
you ask that i'll i'll break down this
way
um we'll talk about uh the audience
first and who we think they are
and then what sort of products services
experiences that we want to provide to
them
how's that yeah great
so i think the people that are
interested in this conversation
let's say the early adopters are people
who think of themselves as global
citizens
in some fashion
that's starting point
second are people who want to make a
difference who have that part of their
identity
or aspire to make a difference
that's our audience also i think those
two references is at least 100 million
people around the planet already
which is pretty comforting to think
about right
that there's that many
and
there's
another third sector
which are the traditional
transformation seeking personal
development you know leadership
type of conversations
um i am absolutely
not only a a derivative of buckminster
fuller but of marsha martin
a name not a lot of people in your
audience may know but really should
because
uh she is uh kind of a living griot you
know a historian and and driver of
personal transformation for the last 50
years of of some of the greatest
consequences one of the
reasons why est became a global
phenomenon in the 70s
and she's one of my mentors what was her
name one more time marcia martin
marshall dot com everybody should go to
marcia martin.com
sign up for her 10 a month library which
has some of the most amazing
transformational work
any of us have ever heard i mean she has
coached and been behind the scenes
coaching some of the greatest leaders
that everybody on this podcast
uh likely follows and listens to name
brand folks you can look her up
marcia martin.com but i mention her
because
um
her whole life of personal
transformation i feel one of the
greatest things most consequential
things she ever put out in the universe
is that
life lives in the conversation you want
life to move in some other direction
that it's not what it is right now it's
going to be because of your conversation
that's a starting point and and our
entire work is sort of built around that
idea which has been germinating me for
25 years since i met her as a student
so i i mention all of this because there
are people who are highly transformed by
this conversation as i said this is the
thing we talked about before about the
accidental personal development side of
this so that's a category as well and we
have something called the agreement
academy
where people who've caught wind of the
fact that they can personally evolve
through this conversation who we just
give them a little package of why don't
you go out and have a conversation 10
times 10 people do some social research
with us see what you learn from that so
it's a little program like that so
that's an audience as well and that gets
me into talking about some of the
products and services we have
the most important
which that is fun the agreement academy
is very much fun
um but the thing that we think is the
scorecard
the thing that's most important to
signify we're having enough
conversations out there
is the release of a treaty
remember i said that basically treaties
is where we create wealth from not
during the war
um and we call this the last treaty
humanity will ever need to sign because
to be signed by humans not nations
we think that's unbreakable that's
beautiful
it's a decentralized approach to
self-government in the same way that
blockchain is a decentralized approach
to money and capital
and there is kind of a unique nft
historic thing associated with that as
well and we're in pre-launch for it now
so anybody listening to my voice that
says it would be great if the world
could actually work this way a way that
you can personally
actually move that ball further
certainly following our social media
obviously that always lets the world
know that people are paying attention to
conversation but if you've looked enough
at our argument as to why humanity needs
its own treaty and we make that argument
in a
another product we have which we call a
survey but it's really like a 30-minute
walk through as to why somebody would
actually sign a treaty on behalf of
themselves in humanity
and we intend to bring that treaty to
fruition with 100 million signers over
five years we expect it will take us to
do
and so we're in pre-launch for that now
and we've told the media that we're
going to get more than 50 000
uh pre-registrations on the day of
release
which means we need people today
to
let us know they like this idea to
participate in that and then we actually
surpass that and gets onto mainstream
media and we can really build this
conversation around the world so be a
very historic act that people could make
every time people hear about what we
want to do they have an obvious
objection of how the hell are you going
to pull that off kind of stuff and our
answer is always well we can pull it off
if people like you can help us
yeah and so that um is basically our
signature product is the treaty in in
pre-release now people can look at the
language of it understand the all on our
website isaiah.org it's very clear uh
from there and then they can decide if
they want to support us just with their
voice and of course if they think that
the media we're doing is good and want
to throw some dollars into it like any
other non-profit we will absolutely
accept that for people who don't feel
they can devote as much time as they
want to and they want us to devote time
for them cash will do that for us
yeah yeah i mean i see that as a
definite possibility i mean you know
look at the the psychedelic world you
know all the people that are donating to
that and all the research that's being
done to that and now that it's kind of
the legalities are being cleaned up
around it there's a lot of people who
are like actually this makes a lot of
sense we can all uh help a lot of people
in this in this
you know this whole
area of exploring our consciousness and
unwinding these things of our identity
that the psychedelics help us do um but
yeah you do see a lot more people
donating to um like even maps
um i can see it as a definite
possibility so this is this might be a
question that's a a bit
not worthwhile because i haven't even
glanced at the treaty or i haven't
looked at the website um
right now but uh
so say i say i sign this treaty what
does my life look like after that so say
i put my name on the list how do i live
differently
afterwards are my interactions different
is my conversations with myself
different
what do you see as a change after after
participating in this
well fortunately i can answer that
question
from real life examples of lots of
people besides me who've been following
this conversation for a few years
and
i remember the first time i had the
realization just before the treaty
existed but the conversation had started
and my friend jim was at an event in
boston and he had heard me talk about
this six months before
and we were having a conversation in
boston at the end of the evening he goes
you know
when daniel first brought up this
conversation i went home that night
and uh
thought about all the things that there
are enough of and the things that are
not enough of you know and i realized i
was fretting about a lot of things i
didn't need to fret about i started to
realize the things that there are not
enough of what i could do something
about like it was just as if it was a
plant you know in terms of me describing
it this way but it was this organic
experience and i found a lot of other
people as well
uh the treaty is a great scorecard for
us
but it's the conversations that produce
the treaty signings in the first place
that's the real product
of our work right so when we
successfully reach 100 million signers
people say well of course you'll extend
that no it'll be 100 million signers
because the product
of that game is all the ripple effect of
the conversations even people who refuse
to sign it i've had people who look at
it think it's fantastic but it's missing
one thing and they won't sign it because
of that one thing
um which again gets us back to how
difficult it is to find agreement like
just because of one thing that they
disagree with they can't you know and
that's that's what it is right
um but that person who won't sign it
loves the work enough that they're
introducing me to other people of
influence and they're still you know
kind of arguing this or that point or
showing up at a clubhouse or whatever
and so what i believe the value we've
done for that individual who didn't sign
the treaty is in some ways just as
important as somebody who signs it now
somebody who signs it
if we do our job right that they really
know what they're signing and continue
to educate them to the level that they
want to you know have more information
on this and deepen this the way that jim
had organically over six months
is we continue to feed
content
and experiences and games and events
which are all demonstrating
collaboration
and if marcia martin and i were here
having a conversation together i would
say marcia would you agree that a lot of
our literature of transformation is
about awareness she's an she's an
awareness
you know
guru right she really understands how to
convey to another human being how to
increase their own awareness in magical
ways
but but but i think that all of the
people that have written over the last
70 years
of this sort of
human potential movement were very
little has been put onto the literature
of demonstration and i don't think
transformation happens without both
awareness and demonstration together for
the most part
um which gets you that question of how
come i've read all these books and my
life hasn't changed
question
so my answer to that is it's going to be
up to us to take that audience attention
make sure that people know that they're
making a commitment
to themselves it's not to us or you know
guru daniel or some sort of silly thing
like that it's just a commitment to
themselves to just do the best they can
to make agreement and really live up to
that
um i don't see how they could fail you
know what i mean
and i don't see how they could improve
of course some will do lots with it and
others do do less but but i think it's
net human positive by the way the phrase
that somebody wanted me to include in
the treaty was net nature positive
and uh and i didn't
agree to that because
um i think that humanity's
sustainability is about itself not about
the planet i think that if humanity is
sustaining itself it will take care of
the planet i think trying to help people
to take care of the planet versus
humanity inadvertently creates a war
between nature and humanity
yeah i mean it creates a separation
right yes and i don't think we should be
seeing it as a default as a separation
because we yeah i mean in my eyes we are
like i said we are of nature we are the
same thing as the planet
yes and and i'm not capable of of
speaking from that place of nature the
way you evocatively do i am very much uh
about how do we work together oh we're
talking about nature great let's do that
you know what i mean look because i love
that because it's it's the part of the
people like us thing that i'm putting
people already think it's too broad what
we're doing but to us we're very laser
focused on this issue
you know that sustainability is about
it's like uh
george carlin if anybody hasn't looked
it up has a great thing about that the
planet will be fine just search george
carlin the planet will be fine that in a
very funny way expresses this
um
yeah so does this answer the question
about the scale like the the idea here
is to make the treaty our
highest record of the conversation in a
way and for each individual that signs
it they are able to you know aspire to a
commitment to make agreement over
conflict wherever they can
and
we then are looking as a content studio
because obviously 100 million people is
de facto a television network in my view
um
and so how do we create those experience
including games where we bring people
together of very little likelihood of
agreeing and figuring out incentives and
ways for them to find agreement without
compromise
agreement with compromise is not is not
what we're talking about at least not to
compromise values or history or or tribe
or whatever it is right i don't have to
join your tribe to agree with you we can
find agreement first you know from where
we sit this is why it's history and
choices together right so that's that's
basically where our strategy is that we
will involve people in this conversation
by creating activities and games and
events
and and turning it into a television
network
and uh and and and uh our business model
for it was will be
that the audience will
in a tokenized way own that television
network uh uh some day near soon
right yeah yeah i really see how the i
feel like even just you you speaking
about it um in me kind of sitting with
you know the hashtag is there enough it
is kind of this i do see how it opens
doors
it's it's this uh it's this lock there's
this key to to locks that like creates
possibility where
i mean if you just if you just word the
question a little bit differently
there's not there's not possibility of
opening right
there's fascinating
uh
part of the conversation we're
opening by realizing that because
it's sometimes a different set of words
that's the same question
okay i'll give you an example
our for-profit company is called impact
launchpad that's a venture student
special impact venture studio
and we ask a question on there
that says how will we find the three and
a half trillion dollars necessary to
invest in the future of humanity and
when i say necessary
the sustainable development goals you
could think of the 17 sustainable
development goals the united nations for
for those who don't know what that is
um
have a price tag associated with them
that's estimated we might debate on the
number whether it's three and a half or
five and a half or whatever it is but
there's a deficit
in what we've already identified
needs to be spent
to save humanity and it's not come from
our existing sources being nations
philanthropy and private investment
so asking that question is kind of is
there enough money
where are we going to find three and a
half trillion dollars to invest in the
future vending does that exist
i mean
there's 24 trillion in the ground in the
democratic republic of congo one of the
poorest countries on earth that has
guess what not very much agreement in a
whole lot of war
we have uh something from seven to nine
quadrillion estimated worth between real
estate
um financial assets outstanding credits
uh art artwork i mean on and on before
we start mining asteroids so do we have
three and a half trillion dollars
i would say we do
but we don't have the agreement somehow
again this is why this is so central to
our professional work everything we've
talked about to this point is if we had
the agreement some agreement
of how we'd actually come up with that
money we could invest that money in
stuff we know it's like saying we're not
going to build that ridge or bridge or
road as far as i'm concerned it's human
infrastructure
so you take the is there enough
conversation you make it much more
specific to that situation in
my relationship with my significant
other there could be an is there enough
style question
[Music]
there too
and that really gets us when you talk
about opening up possibility which must
take place for transformation which is
why marsha you know is such a guru of of
possibility and awareness in in her work
and so are all the great people we
follow always about possibility that
is something we've taken out of our
online conversation so so let me be
specific so it was accidental this
conversation of is there enough but once
i saw the effect it had with people
realized it was a thing oh let's get a
website
and to me it was always about the
hashtag
with a question mark
and you can't put a question mark in a
hashtag
and you can't put it in a domain name
we've we've called these things special
characters as they're not part of
regular conversation was that any wonder
why people are just shouting stuff at
each other and telling people you're
looking at the wrong facts interesting
yeah
and clubhouse has been a real
breakthrough and social audio in general
the clubhouse like saying kleenex right
but but clubhouse and social audio has
given us a way for people to start
asking each other questions which is why
i think it's a breakthrough
[Music]
you know when first when clubhouse first
uh when i first heard about it i had a
couple weeks of just like spending so
much i thought i was like this is the
most revolution there's something about
this i was like this is this is
this is something it was uh
it took the social media um condensing
everything down and the
the display of
kind of like the inherent
virtue i don't know virtue signaling is
the best word but the the inherent like
display that we all put on when we're
communicating through social media
everybody's reading what you're saying
but you're just talking to this person
um
yes something about when when the
clubhouse just the audio only
conversations came about i'm like oh
this is something this is this is really
cool so what what have you guys you guys
have had a lot of um uh would you say
fruitful conversations in clubhouse and
in these audio chat rooms has it changed
the game a lot for you or
for all for everything we do we look at
it as social research all the
conversations we've had around the world
and all that stuff
so this became a mecca of conversation
for us
as well i mean i've had conversations
with some really interesting unsavory
characters
on there that i've been able to actually
make a little agreement with here and
there
um just because i'm always testing
myself how can i make agreement and very
you know it's just kind of my jam at
this point you know in difficult
circumstances and i've learned a lot
from that um
and uh
up to now we've just been visiting other
people's rooms
and talking about what we're doing
and the reaction
let me say
it's been so strong it's been a little
scary
and
it's
it also unveiled something when you talk
about what we need to learn and research
and stuff like that
if you think about it it's obvious when
i say it but over the last 15 or 20
years
the global world order as a concept has
become a nefarious thing after world war
ii it was an aspect of creating freedom
around the world with all of its
hypocrisy of course because it's really
world war ii never ended it just
converted into another war
but the but the u.n declaration of human
rights is a really admirable document
and it's really mostly an american
document it really looks amazingly like
like the bill of rights
um
and like there's a lot of americans
who've never even read it so this is why
i'm you know stating that it's worth a
read
but over the last you know particularly
last 15 20 years the whole concept of a
global world order has become something
of you know little men sitting in a
corner sort of trying to run world
government kind of thing
and i think it's made us safer
environment for nationalism which is
very war-like
and
i'm talking about how to make the world
work for 100 of humanity so if you're
very fearful about world order i sound
like an enemy
and so there were like a group of people
that got together in a room and had like
an important discussion about whatever
daniel's saying and is he part of the
cabal
oh
yeah
so so this this is one of the extremes
that we learned about and what i like to
do is i like to take a weakness and turn
it into a strength if i can legitimately
and um so what i've come to do
proactively in my conversation is
emphasize uh that we're building a world
game not a world order
that we're engaging people to
participate in the only real purpose of
is there enough in the end result with
all the transformations all that
wonderful stuff we talked about is that
the way you win the world game is you
enroll everybody in the world game
i'd love talking about marcia in this
conversation but so much uh that that
i'll i'll emphasize her her history a
little further
is when i showed her some of the work
that we've done like showing my teacher
you know this proud work that i'd come
up with
and um and i put up two slides in front
of her and i said how do you make the
world work for 100 of humanity by
enrolling everyone in the game and this
treaty and this conversation is like a
baby step into the world game and she
looked back and she said you know when
we founded the hunger project which is
one of you know the more important ngos
of the last 35 years
um which was founded by est and warner
earhart
she said that werner announced everybody
what they were going to do they were
like a seminar company at the time and
somebody in the back of the room raised
their hand and said uh we're going to
end world hunger how
and his like immediate response was he
said the first thing we're going to do
is persuade people it can be done
and that's all we're really doing is
selling humanity and the fact that we
can overcome our existential threats we
can survive we do not have to go down
this road of eschatology and oh the end
of the world is a wonderful thing no
it's not right we can survive that is
our job that's what we were put here for
and if we can rule enough people in that
as a mission it but the fact i mean we
have some ideas about how to make the
world work by by investing in it okay
those are not the only ways to make the
world work by far right so if we can
just enroll people that the world game
is their responsibility
boom
that's what we're after
wow you know i must say daniel i feel uh
i feel this sense of uh hopefulness i
think is the right word it's strangely
uh um uh because a lot of the
you know when we i think just the basic
narrative of the state of the world you
know it's kind of this nihilistic like i
don't know it seems like we're kind of
losing our minds and we don't seem to be
able to get on the same page and make
sense of what's going on and hopefully
we face in the right direction hopefully
somebody figures it out you know i feel
like uh the things you're bringing up in
in this conversation give me this sense
of hopefulness of oh yeah we do have the
power of uh
um you know just just through
conversation in inquiring and uh um you
know discussing these things we do of
course have more than enough power to
kind of handle the the quarrels that
seem to face us or may face us in the
future
this is uh i think
it's a
thing for us to be highly compassionate
of ourselves
that in our fear of our existential
challenges we're being responsible in
recognizing what those are
at the end of the day we're still going
to have to ask the question what are we
going to do about it as well
and and i do believe that over time
we'll have less impact
by getting to that question what are we
going to do about it's not
uh unreasonable or
or unfeasible for people to be worried
about about our destruction uh in 20
it's estimated we'll have a billion
people
homeless and without a passport
uh i mean just think like uh-huh uh uh
if it was 100 million was was the was
the projection that would be a hundred
times the syrian crisis and look what
that did to destabilize the world right
so
we're not even beginning to approach a
really big problem like i mean we're
doing our part to hopefully to invest in
some solutions for that how people will
be housed and you know 3d printing and
you know growing food on site and all
that wonderful tech that's out there
again which just needs money in
agreement because money is just an
agreement
but at the end of the day uh
i i hope that it isn't just hope
but feasible possibilities that are
worth failing at compared to doing
nothing you know what i mean at least
agree with me on that that it's worth
trying to do something about
as opposed to just coming up with our
stories
about why we can't
that's i hope the part that is giving
you the experience of hope
yeah no i i i i think i think it very
much is it's a
yeah yeah like i said just to
re-emphasize just like the the door
opening um of this conversation it does
seem like it's uh
no you you get to see more lights on
down the hallway okay want to check out
over there it doesn't seem like there's
any sort of door closing it seems like
um
i don't know
hope seems like to be the word that
sprouts in my mind um daniel we are
getting up here in time i do actually
have to head to the airport like not
after too long um i would love to get
like a just one more summarization of
where to send people um your website um
do you have a date for when the book is
coming out yet do you have that set yet
i don't but it's definitely in the first
quarter of 2023
great um people will see links to it on
the israelites.org website or they can
go to the firstagreement.com
um i would encourage everybody to follow
our social media so we can express to
the world
uh you know the people are paying
attention to our conversation i think
the uh desire to become part of our
relaunch or a pre-launch and sign the
treaty they may need some more
investigation before they do that and i
hope they do i want them to
knowledgeably
know what it is that they're signing up
for so to speak
um and uh i think they'll find you know
if they're on clubhouse joining our
clubhouse room is where they can really
engage us in conversation about
this and then what is it what is your
guys's social media
you'll find it all on is there enough
dot org it links to all of our social
media right there
um
and um
and uh if you even just join our mailing
list every time we add and we have we're
adding social media in pieces as we get
community managers and all the various
social media
um but uh
if they go to is there enough.org
they'll find what is in existence right
now
gotcha okay well and i'll include um
links to that in the bio so listeners if
you're listening just look down below
there should be a link to what you need
to go to and definitely check it out um
daniel i really appreciate your presence
and your time and in your discussion
here with me today man i really um
i'm glad you you guys are doing what
you're doing i think it's awesome i'm
very intrigued um i'm definitely gonna
be diving through that website myself
and i look forward to the book coming
out man it's been a real honor being
with you jacob and i think your
questions are so insightful i can see
why this podcast has so much tension
thank you
appreciate you man all right have a good
rest of your day daniel and then hey
maybe i'll see you around you're in
austin so
maybe i'll cross passes yeah stay in
touch man i would truly love that and i
would love to introduce you to christy
thompson who is that dancing guy uh
individual with a fascinating story of
transformation yeah it sounds amazing
yes shoot me an email i'd love to make
that happen man let's do that okay all
right take care
better daddy
at what age do we learn to have better
conversations with ourselves
[Music]
knowledge is power
you